Aleksandr Melkikh

Information Security Team Lead

Male, 28 6 years experience Master of Engineering



melkih.a.a@gmail.com +7 999 978 6543

I'm an experienced security engineer who loves technologies, complex and distributed services. I know how big tech works and how to make it secure: from an attacking perimeter to the malicious insider.

For the last 2 years I have been working with a multi-cloud infrastructure (primarily Azure) to make Toloka.Al and other Yandex services more secure and compliant.

Skills & Technologies

Azure Security

Azure AD, RBAC, Policy, Azure Kubernetes Service, KeyVault, Log Analytics Workspace

Complex systems security

TLS, authn (OAuth, OIDC), Linux hardening

Yandex.Cloud

IAM, Managed K8S, Compute, VPC

SDLC / AppSec

SCA, SAST (CodeQL, SemGrep), source code security review (Go, Python, Java, Kotlin, JS)

Developing tooling and services

Golang, Python, Terraform

Web Security

Client/server side penetration testing

Languages

English

Upper-Intermediate

Russian

Native

Work Experience

Security Team Lead — Toloka.Al

Leipzig, Germany. Jan, 2023 — present

- Make a multi-cloud (Azure, Yandex.Cloud, Yandex.Deploy) environment of Toloka.Al secure and reliable.
- Made Toloka.Al passed the ISO 27001 & 27701 certifications.
- Made a painless SDLC process, including security design review and source code security review.
- Designed secure Data Warehouse platforms based on Apache Airflow and Databricks.
- Designed a KeyCloak based IAM for user and apps authentication.

Senior Information Security Engineer — Yandex

Moscow, Russia. Sep 2018 — Aug 2019, Mar 2020 — Dec 2022

- Make multi-cloud Yandex projects secure, including: Azure/AWS/Yandex.Cloud asset inventorying, RBAC, secure networking, building golden images, audit trails transfering, etc.
- Building company-wide SCA process: developing tools for checking OSS vulnerabilities, improving protection from malware/protestware OSS.
- Designing and reviewing the security of core components of Yandex infrastructure.
- Training developers in SDLC (during PCI DSS and ISO 27001 certifications) and also <u>Yandex School of Data Analysis</u> students.

Senior Security Specialist (ICS/SCADA/IoT) — Positive Technologies

Moscow, Russia. Sep 2016 — Aug 2018, Aug 2019 — Mar 2020

Participated in 18 projects on the security assessment of industrial facilities (transport, metallurgy, energy, oil/gas industry, etc). Specialized in the following tasks:

- Identification of all potential vulnerabilities in an ICS environment.
- Proprietary networking protocols/firmware analysis.
- Security compliance checking of all relevant standards.

Education

Bauman Moscow State Technical University

B.Eng and M.Eng, Robotics and complex automation. GPA: 4.8 and 4.9 out of 5 respectively.

Made research about network anomaly detection.

Made BSs and MSs thesis about securing Industrial Control Systems.

Professional courses

Offensive Security Certified Professional Apr 2018

Linux system administration, Mail.Ru

Sep 2015 — Jan 2016